Ah, בסיעתא דשמיא, Bisiyata Dishmaya, today's דף Daf is דף ג׳ Daf
Gimel in סנהדרין Sanhedrin and we're going to pick up at the
bottom of ב׳ עמוד ב׳. Bet Amud Bet. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara is dealing with this question about how to read the משנה.
Mishnah. The משנה Mishnah says דיני ממונות Dinei Mamonot are בשלושה bishlosha
and it says and then it seems to give the
specifics: גזל וחבלות Gezel ve-Chavalot etc. But the problem is is that
it's ignoring the classic cases of דיני ממונות, Dinei Mamonot, which are
civil disputes which are not cases of torts, which are cases which
the בבלי Bavli refers to
as הודאות והלוואות, Hoda'ot ve-Halva'ot, admissions and loans, classic civil disputes. So
the first claim of רבי אבהו, Rabbi Abbahu, now the simplest thing
to be to say would be that's what the generic phrase דיני
ממונות Dinei Mamonot means, and גזל וחבלות Gezel ve-Chavalot gets into, you
know, more non-standard cases of civil disputes. But רבי אבהו Rabbi Abbahu
says is no, what we need to do is narrow the scope
of דיני ממונות Dinei Mamonot just to the specifics mentioned in the
משנה Mishnah and to specifically exclude classic civil disputes of הודאות והלוואות.
Hoda'ot ve-Halva'ot. So why are we excluding it? So what רבי אבהו
Rabbi Abbahu says is we're excluding, don't doesn't that need a בית
דין Beit Din of three? Now actually there are some אמוראים Amoraim
that say it doesn't need a בית דין Beit Din of three,
classic civil disputes. But רבי אבהו Rabbi Abbahu says it does. So
in what ways do you mean to exclude it from the משנה?
Mishnah? And the last thing we left off with is the בבלי
Bavli said we're excluding it from the משנה Mishnah to say even
though it needs a בית דין Beit Din of three, it doesn't
need מומחין. Mumchin. It doesn't need people that, now what exactly מומחין
Mumchin mean? רש״י Rashi tells us it means סמיכה, Smicha, which is
the sort of tradition, the passing down of authority from all going
all the way back to משה רבינו Moshe Rabbeinu plus a certain
amount of political authority that it was appointed by the נשיא. Nasi.
So you're actually given, you know, because a judge, it's all very
nice like if you think about our בתי דין Batei Din nowadays
in like outside of ישראל, Yisrael, right, it's very nice that a
בית דין Beit Din rules something, you know, and you might feel
religiously compelled to do it, but where is the political authority that
backs up a court's rulings? So רש״י Rashi also says that they
have the authority of the נשיא. Nasi. Okay, but we'll discuss more
what מומחין Mumchin is. Now the important point to recognize now though
is the concept of a מומחה Mumcheh is linked to the word
of אלהים. Elohim. אלהים Elohim is a word that totally emphasizes that
you represent God and that you have actual power and authority. You
know, so maybe that sort of sense of that political backing. Okay,
and that word tells you the need of מומחין. Mumchin. And what
רבי אבהו Rabbi Abbahu and what we are saying here is that's
only when you start with things like torts, but when you start
with basic civil cases, it needs a בית דין Beit Din but
they don't have to be מומחין Mumchin and they're being excluded from
the משנה. Mishnah. So now the בבלי Bavli wants to understand why
is that? So let's take a look. Okay,
אלא דלא בעינן מומחין. Ela delo ba'inan mumchin. It is like one,
two, three, eight lines from the bottom on ב׳ עמוד ב׳. Bet
Amud Bet. To tell you that those things do not require מומחין.
Mumchin. מאי קסבר, Mai Kasavar, now what is the opinion of the
תנא Tanna of this משנה Mishnah if that's genuinely what he says?
אי קסבר עירוב פרשיות כתוב כאן, I Kasavar Eruv Parshiyot Kasuv Kan,
if he holds that this is a mixture of two different פרשיות
Parshiyot in the תורה, Torah, בעי מומחין, ba'ei mumchin, you should need
מומחין. Mumchin. I'll unpack this in a second. ואי קסבר אין עירוב
פרשיות כתוב כאן, ve-i kasavar ein eruv parshiyot kasuv kan, and if
you're saying it's not a mixture of two different
פרשיות, Parshiyot, שלושה למה לי, shlosha lamah li, why do you need
three? What does this mean? It means that the classic source in
the תורה Torah for the idea of a בית דין Beit Din
of three, the use of the word אלהים Elohim three times, right,
is the פרשה Parshah by that you give somebody something to watch
and they deny it: כי יתן איש אל רעהו כסף או כלים
לשמור וגונב מבית האיש אם ימצא הגנב ישלם שנים אם לא ימצא
הגנב ונקרב בעל הבית אל האלהים אם לא שלח ידו במלאכת רעהו.
ki yiten ish el re'ehu kesef o kelim lishmor vegunav mibet ha'ish
im yimatze haganav yeshalem shenayim im lo yimatze haganav venikrav ba'al habayit
el ha'elohim im lo shalach yado bimlechet re'ehu. Great, did I do
the wrong one? Yeah, על כל דבר פשע על שור על חמור
על שה על שלמה על כל אבידה אשר יאמר כי הוא זה.
al kol devar pesha al shor al chamor al seh al salma
al kol aveda asher yomar ki hu zeh. Great, so it says
כי הוא זה, ki hu zeh, עד האלהים יבא דבר שניהם,
ad ha'elohim yavo devar sheneihem, שניהם אשר
ירשיען אלהים ישלם שנים לרעהו.
sheneihem asher yarshi'un elohim yeshalem shenayim
lere'ehu. I think there's a where's the אלהים Elohim that starts it?
על כל דבר פשע, Al kol devar pesha, thank you.
אשר יאמר כי הוא זה. asher yomar ki hu zeh. No, על
כל דבר פשע
al kol
devar pesha that
was the fourth one.
עד האלהים יבא דבר שניהם, ad ha'elohim yavo devar sheneihem, somebody look
up the פסוק. pasuk. There's a third אלהים. Elohim. Anyways, ונקרב בעל
הבית אל
האלהים
venikrav ba'al habayit
el
ha'elohim אם לא שלח ידו במלאכת רעהו
על כל דבר פשע,
im lo
shalach
yado bimlechet re'ehu al kol devar pesha, right, okay, ונקרב בעל הבית
venikrav ba'al habayit fine. ונקרב בעל הבית אל האלהים venikrav ba'al habayit
el ha'elohim okay, אם לא שלח ידו, im lo shalach yado, אם
לא שלח ידו. im lo shalach yado. Okay, so this is basically
about a claim that it was stolen, you didn't use it for
yourself, and anything אשר יאמר כי הוא זה. asher yomar ki hu
zeh. Now what is אשר יאמר כי הוא זה? asher yomar ki
hu zeh? So here so here's the three uses of אלהים, Elohim,
you need a בית דין Beit Din of three. Now this is
a case of גזילה. gezelah. Why is it a case of גזילה?
gezelah? Because the idea is the שומר shomer is holding on to
the object claiming it's stolen and it wasn't stolen. So he stole
it. So the active holding on, if I, as רש"י Rashi points
out in the משנה, Mishna, if I'm not paying a debt, yes,
I'm stealing money from you, but halachically that's not גזילה. Gezeila. That's
the non-payment and it is what it is. But it's not the
גזילה Gezeila we're talking about, it's not paying up my debts. The
active taking or holding of property that is yours, a physical, a
concrete, specific piece of property that's yours, that's גזילה. Gezeila. So this
or whatever, yeah, this is גזילה. Gezeila. Now, the question is what
does אשר יאמר כי הוא זה Asher yomar ki hu zeh mean?
So the בבלי Bavli is the גמרא Gemara says that this means
that we're debating that this phrase "this is it" is a phrase
that refers to מודה במקצת. Modeh b'miktzas. Okay? Where it's like I
say you owe me, you know, three objects, and you say, "No,
no, no, I only owe you this object." And this one was
stolen anyway. Okay? So I'm making a larger claim and you're only
admitting to part of it. That's the כי הוא זה. Ki hu
zeh. So the question is, in a classic case of שומרים, Shomrim,
the basic issue is you as a שומר Shomer have to swear
that something happened, you know, that you didn't misuse it. Why does
there need to be a large claim that you're admitting to part
of it, right? If I could be demanding the whole object and
you could be denying the whole object, isn't that a classic oath
of שומר? Shomer? So that leads to a debate in the גמרא
Gemara whether this thing of כי הוא זה Ki hu zeh is
really referring to the שומר Shomer case. There's a very strange idea,
but one that we might posit in for that the actual שומר,
Shomer, you do not need מודה במקצת. Modeh b'miktzas. Actual שומר, Shomer,
the שומר Shomer denies the whole thing and he still has to
take a שבועה. Shvuah. When do you need, when is a שבועה,
Shvuah, right, this is about making an oath, right, when is a
שבועה Shvuah required, when is a שבועה Shvuah required partial admission? In
a case of a loan. I say I lent you a hundred
dollars. If you say, "No, you never lent me a penny," or
"I paid it all back," you don't admit anything, you don't take
any oath. If you have a partial admission, the classic idea of
מודה במקצת, Modeh b'miktzas, then כי הוא זה, Ki hu zeh, though
this is the part I owe you. I owe you fifty, but
fifty I paid back, or fifty I didn't borrow, then you take
an oath, that's מודה במקצת. Modeh b'miktzas. So if כי הוא זה
Ki hu zeh is not telling you that a שומר Shomer requires
a partial admission, it's telling you that a case of a loan
requires a partial admission. So this thing is talking about loans, not,
not talking, I gotta get another pen, not talking about שומרים. Shomrim.
Okay? And that's עירוב פרשיות. Eruv parshiyos. These are two separate פרשיות.
Parshiyos. There's a פרשה Parsha about שומר Shomer which does not require
כי הוא זה, Ki hu zeh, and then stuck in the middle
of this פרשה Parsha of שומר Shomer is a discussion of partial
admissions of loans, כי הוא זה. Ki hu zeh. That's עירוב פרשיות.
Eruv parshiyos. Why is that relevant? Because if it is עירוב פרשיות,
Eruv parshiyos, then embedded in here is a discussion of loans. And
then it is telling you that the requirement of a בית דין
Beis din of three learned from the word אלוהים, Elohim, which teaches
you מומחים Mumchim as well, not just three, but three מומחים, Mumchim,
also applies to loans, because a loan case is embedded in here.
But if it's not עירוב פרשיות Eruv parshiyos and this is all
just about שומר, Shomer, then you don't have the idea of מומחים
Mumchim by loans, but you also don't have the idea of three.
So that's what the, that's what the גמרא Gemara is saying is
make up your mind. If there's a case of loans written in
here, then you should need מומחים. Mumchim. And if there's a case
of loans not written in here, then how do you know you
even need three by a case of a loan? Okay, so let's
read that again. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: מאי קסבר?
Mai kasvar? What is he of the opinion of? אי קסבר עירוב
פרשיות כתיב כאן, Ei kasvar eruv parshiyos ksiv kan, it's a two
separate פרשיות Parshiyos mixed together, לבעי נמי מומחים. Libei nami mumchim. So
then it's embedded in this פרשה Parsha and it has three אלוהים,
Elohims, you should need three and you should need מומחים. Mumchim. ואי
קסבר אין עירוב פרשיות כתיב כאן, V'ei kasvar ein eruv parshiyos ksiv
kan, and if this case isn't dealing with loans, so שלושה למה
לי, Shelosha lama li, how do you even know you need three?
לעולם קסבר עירוב פרשיות כתיב כאן, Le'olam kasvar eruv parshiyos ksiv kan,
it is three, it is dealing with the case of loans. ובדין
הוא דלבעי נמי מומחים, U'vdin hu d'libei nami mumchim, and technically you're
right, even loans requires
מומחים. Mumchim. והאי דלא בעינן מומחים, V'hai d'la bainan mumchim, so why
is it being excluded from the משנה Mishna and you don't need
מומחים? Mumchim? משום דרבי חנינא, Mishum d'Rabbi Chanina, because of the teaching
of רבי חנינא. Rabbi Chanina. דאמר רבי חנינא דבר תורה, D'amar Rabbi
Chanina dvar Torah, from it's a, it's an analogy to רבי חנינא.
Rabbi Chanina. Similar to something רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina teaches. רבי חנינא
Rabbi Chanina teaches from a biblical perspective, אחד דיני ממונות ואחד דיני
נפשות בדרישה וחקירה. Echad dinei mamonos v'echad dinei nefashos b'drisha v'chakira. Whether
you're dealing with דיני ממונות Dinei mamonos or דיני נפשות, Dinei nefashos,
whether civil or capital crimes, you have to cross-examine the witnesses and
get the exact time and location and so on. שנאמר משפט אחד
יהיה לכם, Shene'emar mishpat echad yihyeh lachem, one law for you, and
this is and this is linking together, you know, a דיני ממונות
Dinei mamonos and דיני נפשות Dinei nefashos in the context of that
פסוק. Pasuk. So you really should require the same דרישה וחקירה. Drisha
v'chakira. מה טעם אמרו, Mah ta'am amru,
well,
we'll get to that, he's talking about דרישה וחקירה. Drisha v'chakira. ומה
טעם אמרו דיני ממונות לא בעינן דרישה וחקירה. U'mah ta'am amru dinei
mamonos lo bainan drisha v'chakira. So why did the rabbis remove that
requirement from monetary issues? כדי שלא תנעול דלת בפני לווין, kedei shelo
tin'ol delet bifnei lovin, in order not to make it hard for
people to lend money. Again, if it's too hard for, if, if
the rabbis are going to so crazy cross-examine the witnesses, like again,
I get nothing out of lending you money. I don't get interest,
I don't get whatever, you might not pay it up. So as
תוספות Tosfos sort of says, it's very easy for me to, any
tiny little bump to me is a good enough reason not to
lend you money. So we have to really pave the path. So
we're going to make it very easy and not demand דרישה וחקירה.
drishah v'chakirah. Now there's an interesting question: does that mean we also
don't demand דרישה וחקירה drishah v'chakirah in other דיני ממונות? dinei mamanos?
How about cases of torts? How about cases of גזילה? gezelah? How
about cases of, you know, of like a whole different range of
possible issues,
קנס? knas? How about there? But you know, it sounds from here
that in all דיני ממונות dinei mamanos we remove דרישה וחקירה. drishah
v'chakirah. Okay. And תוספות Tosfos says there could be a good reason,
because it's very hard for you to bring evidence against me, then
I'm not going to be so careful that my ox doesn't go
running around and goring your ox, and I'm not going to be
so careful that, you know, that I'm not sort of accidentally like
driving on your property or something, you know? What?
גזל gezel be rampant.
גזל gezel be rampant. So תוספות Tosfos says we remove the need
of דרישה וחקירה drishah v'chakirah by דיני ממונות, dinei mamanos, as opposed
to כדי שלא תנעול דלת בפני לווין, kedei shelo tin'ol delet bifnei
lovin, we remove the need of דרישה וחקירה drishah v'chakirah by דיני
ממונות dinei mamanos כדי לנעול דלת בפני גזלנין. kedei lin'ol delet bifnei
gazlanin. Okay. In order to make it harder, you know, we don't
want people to, to feel that they're not going to get prosecuted.
It's actually, by the way, do you know, do you know what's
the level of evidence needed? What's the level of evidence needed for
or for as for a criminal trial? Right? It's beyond a reasonable
doubt. Do you know what the evidence needed is for a civil
trial? Preponderance of evidence. It does not have to be beyond a
reasonable doubt. So there are different thresholds actually for that. Okay. So
we completely removed דרישה וחקירה drishah v'chakirah by
דיני ממונות. dinei mamanos. Okay. So that's what רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina
teaches. So therefore the גמרא Gemara says, and therefore the implication is
by analogy, we're going to remove the need of מומחין mumchin by
loans, not by all דיני ממונות, dinei mamanos, right? גזילה gezelah and
חבלות, chabalos, by the whole משנה Mishnah you need מומחין. mumchin. But
specifically by loans, we remove the need for מומחין. mumchin. And here
תוספות Tosfos says why, like why not just remove it from all
דיני ממונות? dinei mamanos? And תוספות Tosfos says no, no, the point
I said a minute ago, which was, loans I get nothing out
of lending you money. So I am, the tiniest problem is going
to prevent me from lending you money. So for loans, we really
have to remove every obstacle. So analogous to the way that רבי
חנינא Rabbi Chanina said by all דיני ממונות dinei mamanos we remove
דרישה וחקירה, drishah v'chakirah, when it comes to loans, we remove the
need of מומחין. mumchin. Okay. So that's the answer. It's rabbinic and
that's why, and it's in order to make it easier to lend
money. That's one read of the משנה. Mishnah.
Well, why can't you just say that וסבור מיניה vesabur mineih can
say, I mean, if you take this at its face value, that
only in loans you don't need דרישה וחקירה drishah v'chakirah and you
don't need מומחין mumchin because of what you just said, but the
rest of ממונות mamanos you might need דרישה וחקירה? drishah v'chakirah?
Okay, so תוספות Tosfos discusses that. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara
says like this. It's possible, right?
What's ממונות mamanos have to do with any pressure on the,
because if תוספות Tosfos says like this, as that if you,
you damage my car, then I need to get compensated and even
if the מומחין בית דין mumchin Beis Din is, you know, is
ten miles away or in the next town, I'm going to go
there because I want to get you to pay me up. But
I'm not going to lend you money if the only way I'm
going to get my money back is by traveling to the next
town to go to the מומחין בית דין. mumchin Beis Din. Any
tiny little obstacle is going to make it not worth my while
to lend you money in the first
place.
But does מומחין mumchin mean that they can actually affect, like the
הלכה halacha or they can affect change?
That might be, but we're going to hold off that question for
now.
Okay. And it's not you know, that's always the case, because there's
a תקנה takkanah or גזירה gezeirah that we sometimes ignore the fact.
Right, well, that is the point. We do always need מומחין. mumchin.
Whatever the metaphysics is, we do always need it in principle. Now
the גמרא Gemara says like this. אלא מעתה, Ela me'ata, if that's
true, that you're saying that it could be
even non-מומחין mumchin and that you're trying to do it to make
it easier to lend money, טעו לא ישלמו, ta'u lo yeshalmu,
then the principle is that when the בית דין Beis Din consists
of מומחין, mumchin, they are protected from liability. And if they ruled
incorrectly, you can't come after the judges to get compensation. You can't
sue a judge for, you know, judicial
misconduct, but judicial malpractice. You can't. Alright, alright, we'll get to when
you can, but as a general rule you can't. But if the
judge was not a מומחה, mumcheh, you can get recompensed if they
ruled incorrectly and caused you a loss of money. So it says,
one minute... If you're trying to make it easy for the לווה
loveh to find a בית דין, Beis Din, and you don't have
to be מומחה, mumcheh, then you should also say that there's not
going to be the judges won't have to pay. Because if you're
going to say that the judges have this
malpractice, nobody's going to want to be a judge,
you're never going to get a בית דין Beis Din together. Okay?
אלא מעתה Ella me-atah says the גמרא, Gemara, תו לא לא ישלמו,
tu lo lo yishalmu, then you should say that even if they
make a mistake they shouldn't have to pay or else you'll never
get a בית דין. Beis Din. No, the גמרא Gemara says כל
שכן איתנא דאיתא לפני לווה. kol she-kein atana de-itta lifnei loveh. No,
no, no, if there was malpractice, then that's going to be even
a bigger
reason for me not to lend money because I'm going to say
I'm going to lend money and I'm going to bring it to
a court and if the court is irresponsible I'm never going to
be able to get my money back from those cases that they
mishandle. So you need to have, even though it might limit the
people who want to serve on a court, you need to have
the right for me to sue for
malpractice because if I don't I'm going to be that much more
hesitant to lend money in the first place. Okay, but anyway we've
introduced the interesting idea that a court made of הדיוטות hedyotot you
can get, you can sue for
malpractice. I should say, one of the things an opening סוגיא sugya
does because again notice that this whole idea of reading the משנה
Mishna as דיני ממונות dinei mamonot is limited to גזילות וחבלות gezeilot
ve-chavalot and we mean to exclude other cases is not a simple
read of the משנה Mishna which the גמרא Gemara is about to
say. But often an opening סוגיא sugya in the גמרא Gemara what
it does is it uses some type of side issue to introduce
you to some of the major themes that you're going to be
seeing in the פרק. perek. So in this little opening סוגיא, sugya,
we've already introduced us to an idea of אלהים Elohim is the
basis for a בית דין. Beis Din. Three אלהים, Elohims, we haven't
said it but we've also alluded to it, is the basis for
a בית דין Beis Din of three. It's the basis of, there's
an idea of מומחין mumchin and that's learned from
אלהים. Elohim. הודאות והלוואות Hoda'ot ve-halva'ot might not require מומחין. mumchin. If
you're not a מומחה mumcheh then you have to pay if there's
a case of malpractice. דיני ממונות dinei mamonot and דיני נפשות dinei
nefashot in principle both require דרישה וחקירה derisha ve-chakira but we've removed
the requirement from דיני ממונות. dinei mamonot. We've introduced you to a
lot of ideas about what are some of the parameters and some
of the differences around בתי דינים Batei Dinim between מומחה mumcheh and
non-מומחה, mumcheh, דיני ממונות dinei mamonot and דיני נפשות dinei nefashot and
so on. So that's part of what this opening סוגיא sugya is
doing. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues like this. It says
like this. אי הכי Iy hachi says the גמרא, Gemara, תרתי קתני,
tarti katanei, so if the משנה Mishna
why do you read the משנה Mishna to be saying, to be
saying
דיני ממונות dinei mamonot is only גזילות וחבלות? gezeilot ve-chavalot? Why not,
if they have these two different categories, then why not read it
as saying both things, as saying both different categories? Why not read
it דיני ממונות בשלושה הדיוטות dinei mamonot bishlosha hedyotot that דיני ממונות
dinei mamonot refers to loans and therefore that refers to three but
three that are non-מומחה mumcheh and גזילות וחבלות בשלושה מומחין gezeilot ve-chavalot
bishlosha mumchin and גזילות וחבלות gezeilot ve-chavalot are three but three מומחין?
mumchin? Meaning why did you have to read that הודאות והלוואות hoda'ot
ve-halva'ot are not referred to in the משנה? Mishna? Say that דיני
ממונות dinei mamonot refers to הודאות והלוואות hoda'ot ve-halva'ot and that there
are two separate categories. There's the first case of הודאות והלוואות hoda'ot
ve-halva'ot that doesn't need מומחין mumchin and everything else does need מומחין.
mumchin. ועוד. Ve-od. So now we're just challenging Rabbi Abba's read of
the משנה. Mishna. ועוד, Ve-od, שלושה שלושה למה לי? shelosha shelosha lama
li? If it really meant דיני ממונות, dinei mamonot, i.e. גזילות וחבלות,
gezeilot ve-chavalot, why did it say דיני ממונות בשלושה גזילות וחבלות בשלושה?
dinei mamonot bishlosha gezeilot ve-chavalot bishlosha? That seems to clearly say that
those are separate cases, not the same case. Right? So the better
read of the משנה Mishna is that דיני ממונות dinei mamonot exactly
does refer to loans and it actually is saying both loans need
three and גזילות וחבלות gezeilot ve-chavalot need three. It's not excluding loans,
it means loans. So the גמרא Gemara says אלא אמר רבא, ella
amar Rava, so fine, that's how Rava's going to read it. This
is clearly the better read of the משנה. Mishna. תרתי קתני. tarti
katanei. It does mean both. דיני ממונות dinei mamonot means loans are
three and גזילות וחבלות gezeilot ve-chavalot which are other cases of torts
are three. Whether you need מומחה mumcheh by loans or not, that
we can debate. Rabbi Abba says you don't need מומחה mumcheh by
loans, and we had the discussion why, but in terms of the
read of the משנה, Mishna, it's not excluding loans, actually the first
phrase דיני ממונות dinei mamonot means loans. Loans need three and torts
need three, and גזילות וחבלות gezeilot ve-chavalot need three. Okay. Now that
we've introduced this question of does, do loans need three and Rabbi
Abba says they do but they don't need to be מומחה, mumcheh,
we're now going to open up the opportunity to discuss other opinions
that maybe cases that are loans do not need three. Okay? So
let's take a look. משום דרבי חנינא... mishum de-Rabbi Chanina... Okay. אלא
אמר רבא תרתי קתני משום דרבי חנינא. ella amar Rava tarti katanei
mishum de-Rabbi Chanina. It is two, it does mean both. He says
based on רבי חנינא's Rebbe Chanina point that there's a difference between
מומחין mumchin and not מומחין. mumchin. I mean, you know, רבי חנינא's
Rebbe Chanina point about דרישה וחקירה, derishah ve-chakirah, excuse me, that you
know that the Rabbis removed דרישה וחקירה derishah ve-chakirah by דיני ממונות.
dinei mamonot. And similarly, there's a difference between loans and not loans
in terms of מומחין, mumchin, but they are two separate cases in
the משנה. Mishnah. דיני ממונות Dinei mamonot needs three, and that would
be without מומחין, mumchin, and גזלות וחבלות gezelot va-chabalot needs three, and
that would be with מומחין. mumchin. Okay, and now the גמרא Gemara
turns to discussing this question of what is the minimum size of
a בית דין Beit Din by a standard civil case. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this. רב אחא בריה דרב איקא אמר מדאורייתא
חד נמי כשר. Rav Acha b’rei de-Rav Ika amar mi-de’oraita chad nami
kashar. You know, going back to this question of what's the minimum
size of a בית דין? Beit Din? He says from the דאורייתא
de-oraita perspective really one is enough. Okay, now he presumably means, does
he mean the whole משנה, Mishnah, all cases, even cases of torts,
or does he mean at least what we've been discussing about the
case of דיני ממונות? dinei mamonot? Because as רש"י Rashi points out,
remember if you say אי הכי פרשיות כתיב כאן ei hachi parshiyot
ketiv kan and we're not dealing with loans, then fine, cases of
גזילה gezelah requires three, but maybe cases of loans requires less. So
he says, you know what, it's true, דיני ממונות dinei mamonot at
least if it's certainly if it's loans types of cases, not torts,
doesn't really require three. So, what are torts? Torts are damages, like
it's like גזלות וחבלות. gezelot va-chabalot. I damaged you, you know, I
stole from you, I damaged your property, my ox gored your ox.
Okay. So he says מדאורייתא חד נמי כשר. mi-de’oraita chad nami kashar.
Sorry. Really one is enough. And minimum
certainly in the case of loans, maybe even in all דיני ממונות.
dinei mamonot. Anyway, שנאמר: she-ne’emar: בצדק תשפוט עמיתך. Be-tzedek tishpot amitecha. With
justice you shall judge your friend, and תשפוט tishpot is in the
singular. Okay, so if that's true, that you really only need a,
what do you call it, you really only need one, so why
did they require three? Even in cases of loans, we all know
that the default is you need three in practice. אלא משום
יושבי קרנות. Ela mishum yoshei kranot. Because of the cheapos that hang
around on the street corners. Okay, meaning like the, you know, the
people that are sitting around wasting their time, not doing anything. What
does that mean? So it means that if you take a look
at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says יושבי קרנות, yoshei kranot, רש"י Rashi
says like this,
the last of the narrow lines of רש"י: Rashi: תגרין שאין בקיאין
בטיב דינין וישטו את החייב ויחייבו את הזכאי. Tagrin she-ein be-ki’in be-tiv
dinin ve-yestu et ha-chayav ve-yachayavu et ha-zakai.
רש"י Rashi says this builds on the point that loans does not
need מומחין. mumchin. Okay, once we've introduced the idea that loans does
not need מומחין, mumchin, so then we've got a problem. If you
don't need a מומחה, mumcheh, so then you get somebody who's a
complete, you know, ignoramus. Oh, I'm going to have, you know, I'm
going to have Joe Schmo be my, be my דיין. dayan. So
you combine the idea that you don't need מומחין mumchin and the
idea that you only need one, and you've got a real בית
דין Beit Din that is completely irresponsible and doesn't know anything. So
therefore, once we started with this idea that you don't need מומחין,
mumchin, we increased the need of the court to require three. For
three, hopefully one person knows what they're doing. At least that's the
hope. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, so the גמרא Gemara says,
אטו בתלתא מי לא הוי יושבי קרנות? atu be-telata mi lo havei
yoshei kranot? So what, says the גמרא, Gemara, you can't get three
good-for-nothings together in a court? Like, you know, even if you get
three, who says anybody knows what they're doing? So the גמרא Gemara
says no, אי אפשר דלא שכיח חד דגמיר. iy efshar de-la shechiach
chada de-gamir. There must be one of those, if three people are
agreeing to serve in a court, hopefully one of them has some
idea what they're doing. I don't know if that's true, but anyway,
that's the assertion. אלא מעתה, Ela me-ata, says the גמרא, Gemara, similar
to what it said before, לא ישלמו, lo yishalmu, they shouldn't have
to pay. Since you want to encourage, like the sense being that
if you make them pay, all the responsible people will leave. Like
if you've got a lot of, you know, know-nothings, you know, willing
to serve on a court because there's no criteria, and so then,
you know, it's the people who know, they're the more responsible people.
So they're going to, you know, be more hesitant to be playing
this role. So if you tell me I've got to pay, it's
like, let these jokers do it. I'm not going to be on
the court and have to pay, and then you're just going to
make it that much more likely that the court is going to
be, you know, be made up of jokers if you're going to
make people pay. So the גמרא Gemara says, no, כל שכן
איטפי יושבי קרנות. kol she-ken ittefi yoshei kranot. No, the גמרא Gemara
says the opposite is true. If you say that you're going to
have to, the judges will have to pay, that'll actually weed out
the jokers because, you know, because people hopefully at some level will
realize they don't really know what they're doing. Like, oh look, this
is כבוד, kavod, I get to be on the court. But if
you're going to tell me that I'm going to have to pay
if I make a mistake, I'm going to think twice. So the
גמרא Gemara says rather than that liability scaring away the responsible people,
it'll actually scare away the irresponsible people. Okay, but now what we've
said is, we've introduced the idea that a case of loans does
not require מומחין. mumchin. And now what we've said is actually
maybe דאורייתא de-oraita really one is suffices. But because it also doesn't
require מומחין, mumchin, we had to insist on three in order to
ensure. that somebody might know what they're doing on the court. Okay.
So the גמרא Gemara says: מאי איכא בין רבא לרב אחא בריה
דרב איקא? Mai ika bein Rava leRav Acha brei deRav Ika? What
difference would there be? They both at the end of the day
agree that you need three and they don't have to be מומחין.
Mumchin. What difference does it make if you started by saying one
and you ended with three or you started by saying three? At
the end of the day they all agree that for cases of
loans you need three but they don't have to be מומחין. Mumchin.
So what difference would there be? So the גמרא Gemara says: איכא
בינייהו, Ika beina'ihu, the difference would
be, איכא בינייהו דאמר שמואל, Ika beina'ihu de'amar Shmuel, which שמואל Shmuel's
teaching, that what does שמואל Shmuel say? שנים שדנו דיניהם דין אלא
שנקרא בית דין חצוף. Shnayim shedanu dineihem din ela shenikra beit din
chatzuf. בדיעבד Bidi'avad if you had two people ruling, it's a good
judgment, but it's a you know, it's a חוצפה Chutzpah that they
basically violated the proper parameters, but it's not invalid. Now the so
would you accept that בדיעבד Bidi'avad a בית דין Beit din less
than three would be a legitimate ruling? So the גמרא Gemara says:
לרבא לית ליה דשמואל, LeRava layis lei deShmuel, רבא Rava who says
that from the תורה Torah you need three, okay, even though we
don't need מומחין Mumchin but the תורה Torah you need three, maybe
rabbinically maybe we removed מומחין, Mumchin, he would say that if you
have less than three it's completely an invalid ruling. רב אחא בריה
דרב איקא אית ליה דשמואל, Rav Acha brei deRav Ika is lei
deShmuel, רב אחא בריה דרב איקא Rav Acha brei deRav Ika would
agree to שמואל Shmuel and would say that even though the rabbis
required three, they would post facto be okay with two. Obviously you'd
be in violation of the guidelines of the rabbis, it's בית דין
חצוף, Beit din chatzuf, okay, but you at the end of the
day would be he would accept that בדיעבד Bidi'avad it would work.
Now the interesting question is, well if that's true what about if
there's one? Maybe let one person בדיעבד Bidi'avad work. So it could
be there maybe he felt no no no there even בדיעבד Bidi'avad
the rabbis wouldn't allow it. Why is two better than one? Well
first of all you know we're going to see later the גמרא's
Gemara's going to say אל תהי דן יחידי שאין דיין יחידי אלא
אחד. Al tehi dan yechidi she'ein dayan yechidi ela echad. Don't be
a sole judge, the only sole judge that exists in this world
is God. You know that the idea of taking all of the
authority onto yourself, talk about חוצפה, Chutzpah, that word about like I
by myself can be the one to arbitrate what's right and wrong,
that you don't have to you know consult with anybody else or
get any other perspective on it, so obviously that could be a
problem. And the other point is that in a בית דין Beit
din of three how many do you actually need to vote in
favor of one side? Two. So if you have a בית דין
Beit din of two and it's a split vote they're not going
to come to a decision. The only way a בית דין Beit
din of two will come to a decision is if they both
agree that one of the you know on a פסק. Psak. So
that is the same that you would have, then you could imagine
if the two of you agreed that I was right here and
הלל Hillel was wrong, then even if we had a third guy
I would still win because I still got two votes and I
only needed two out of three votes. Okay so that's why they
might בדיעבד Bidi'avad accept two, A because they really might have found
one is deeply problematic that you think you could be the sole
arbiter of right and wrong, and number two, two means that I
would have won with three anyway. Now not necessarily because if there
was a third person he would have convinced you both that you
were wrong, fine. But at least in theory I've got the two
votes that I need. Okay but that idea works if you say
in principle you only need one. Then we could בדיעבד Bidi'avad and
we could say but we're going to demand three but בדיעבד Bidi'avad
we'll be okay with two. But if in principle you need three
then anything less than three even post facto will not be valid.
You have a question? No that's it yeah. The judicial...
no no no, Eric has a question.
Yeah I'm just wondering without מומחין Mumchin is there any
any minimum requirement?
Yeah it doesn't sound like it. It sounds like יושבי קרנות. Yoshei
kranot. You go you go to the people smoking on the corner,
those people that are just hanging out doing the you know those
good for nothings. Right that's funny though there's no minimum requirement after
that. Okay but we'll continue to see that. But yes. But you
know as I said what the גמרא Gemara now did based on
this almost artificial question of how to read the opening line of
the משנה, Mishnah, was it introduced us to a lot of really
important ideas. Whether you need מומחין, Mumchin, what's the minimum size of
the בית דין, Beit din, the difference between הודאות והלוואות Hoda'ot vehalva'ot
and other types of דיני ממונות, Dinei mamonot, the difference between דיני
ממונות Dinei mamonot and דיני נפשות. Dinei nefashot. We got a nice
little overview of some of the main issues that we're going to
be dealing with which is a classic opening סוגיא Sugya in the
גמרא. Gemara. Okay let's take a look now as we move to
the next part of the משנה. Mishnah. נזק וחצי נזק, Nezek vechatzi
nezek,
damages and half damages, needs three. So the גמרא Gemara says נזק
היינו חבלות. Nezek hainu chavalot.
Why did you have to say damages? You already said גזילות וחבלות,
Gezelot vechavalot, theft and personal injury, and personal injury includes damage. One
of the things you pay for for personal injury is damage. Now
you could say damages is property damage as opposed to personal damage,
but it's almost like if damaging your person requires three, obviously property
damage requires three. So why anyway do you have to mention this?
So the גמרא Gemara says משום דקבעי למתני חצי נזק. Mishum dekaba'i
lemisni chatzi nezek. No because we wanted to move to the case
of half damages. And that was a non-standard case, that might be...
No, because we wanted to move to the case of half damages.
And that was a non-standard case. That might be a case of
a fine. That's not direct compensation. You're not paying the full amount.
So that might have been a different category. So תנן נמי נזק
שלם. tnan nami nezek shalem. So therefore we taught the case of
full damages. So חצי נזק, chatzi nezek, so half damages, says the
גמרא, Gemara, נמי היינו חבלות, nami hainu chavalos, isn't that implicit? It's
still paying for damage. Now, again, half damages is when my unhabituated
ox or other animal, whatever, gores the first three times, so because
it was an unlikely event, I only pay half. So the גמרא
Gemara is saying if you're already telling me that you're going to
pay full damages when it's habituated and that that's you're going to
need a three, why is it different to tell me the case
of half damages needs three? And if you're going to tell me
when you injure somebody you pay three, personal injury, so isn't this
also obvious you need three? So the גמרא Gemara says no, תני
ממונא ותני קנסא. tani mamona vetani knasa. No, there is a difference.
Half is not seen as compensation, since it's not full, it's seen
as a type of a fine and therefore it's a different category,
so we have to teach it separately. פלגא נזקא?
palga nizka? What? פלגא נזקא?
palga nizka?
Well that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to say. הניחא למאן
דאמר פלגא נזקא קנסא. hani cha leman deamar palga nizka knasa. So
this is a classic debate in בבא קמא. Bava Kamma. Why do
you pay half when your ox gores the first three times? So
there's basically the simple way of explaining it is everybody agrees that
it is a borderline case of whether you had negligence or not.
The question
about borderline cases is which side of the border does it fall
on? If you say you were just barely negligent, okay, but so
that's why we're only making you pay half,
because even though technically you were negligent, since you were just over
the line, we're going to go easy on you and only make
you pay half. That would be פלגא נזקא ממונא. palga nizka mamona.
You really are negligent, you really should be paying full, we went
easy on you, but your half payment is still compensation. But the
other approach is you were on the other side of the border.
You were just miss being negligent. But because you were so close,
we're not going to let you get off scot-free because then you're
going to be irresponsible, we're going to make you pay half even
though technically you should be exempt to make you more careful. So
that means it's קנס. knas. It's not really a compensation, it's a
fine. Okay, so that's the debate. So the גמרא Gemara says הניחא
למאן דאמר פלגא נזקא קנסא. hani cha leman deamar palga nizka knasa.
If half payment is a קנס, knas, we get why it's being
treated as a separate category here. אלא למאן דאמר פלגא נזקא ממונא,
ela leman deamar palga nizka mamona, but if the half payment is
actually monetary compensation, so why do you need to teach me? We've
already taught that for damages you pay, you need a בית דין
Beis Din of three. מאי איכא למימר, mai ika lemeimar, why are
we teaching this case? אלא איידי דקבעי למיתני תשלומי כפל ותשלומי ארבעה
וחמשה, ela aidi dekabei lemisni tashlumei kefel vetashlumei arba'a vachamisha, because we're
going to get the cases which everybody agrees is a קנס, knas,
paying double for burglary, four and five for stealing an ox or
a sheep and slaughtering it and selling it. So that case clearly
is not compensation but a fine. דממונא שאינו משתלם בראש. demamona she'eino
mishtalem berosh. And that is money that is not paid just the
base, you know, payment of compensation, but it's different than compensation because
it's in addition to and it's a fine and it's two and
four and five times. So since that case has to be taught,
the case of כפל וארבעה וחמשה, kefel ve'arba'a vechamisha, so תני נמי
חצי נזק, tani nami chatzi nezek, so therefore once we had to
teach the case of two and four and five, we're going to
teach the case of a half, which even if technically it's ממונא,
mamona, but you know, it's similar that it's not the full payment.
It's not just the standard full payment.
דממונא שאינו משתלם בראש. demamona she'eino mishtalem berosh. One is not full
payment because it's more, one is not full payment because it's less.
But once we're going to teach the cases of two, four, and
five, we're going to teach the case of a half. And איידי
דקבעי למיתני חצי נזק, aidi dekabei lemisni chatzi nezek, and then once
we're going to teach the case of half damages, תני נמי נזק,
tani nami nezek, we also teach damages. But it's true, once we
say גזלות וחבלות, gezelos vechavalos, I sort of put that under the
rubric of torts. So once we say torts, we didn't really have
to say נזק nezek and חצי נזק. chatzi nezek. But because we
had to move on to the cases of fines, כפל וארבעה וחמשה,
kefel ve'arba'a vechamisha, we're going to deal with נזק nezek and חצי
נזק, chatzi nezek, which is like the nice transition category to get
us to the case of fines. Okay. And now the גמרא Gemara
finally,
now that we've dealt with some of those very opening phrases in
the משנה, Mishna, the גמרא Gemara now finally turns to what we
had alluded to before and what we saw in the ירושלמי. Yerushalmi.
And here you see the parallels with the ירושלמי Yerushalmi of where
do we know the basis that you need three? Okay. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this, שלשה מנלן, shlosha minalan, where do you
know you need three to make a בית דין? Beis Din? תנו
רבנן. tanu rabbanan. And this is what we said, ונקרב בעל הבית
אל האלהים, venikrav ba'al habayis el ha'elohim, הרי כאן אחד, harei kan
echad, one אלהים Elohim is one. עד האלהים יבא דבר שניהם, ad
ha'elohim yavo devar sheneihem, הרי כאן שנים, harei kan shenayim, two. אשר
ירשיעון אלהים, asher yarshi'un elohim, הרי כאן שלשה. harei kan shlosha. So
three אלהים, Elohims, three judges. דברי רבי יאשיה. divrei Rabbi Yoshiya. רבי
יונתן אומר, Rabbi Yonasan omer, Rabbi Yonatan says ראשון תחלה נאמר ואין
דורשין תחלות. rishon techila ne'emar ve'ein dorshin techilos. You might remember we
saw this exactly in the ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. He says no, the first
אלהים Elohim is needed because you need to have a subject in
the, you know, you need to refer to them. So you can't
start counting those to tell you how many. That's just פשט. pshat.
You just needed that word in the פסוק. pasuk. Okay. You don't
count the first occurrence of a word to get to some technical
halachic hermeneutic, you know, or halachic conclusion. ואין דורשין תחלות. ve'ein dorshin
techilos. אלא עד האלהים יבא. ela ad ha'elohim yavo. עד האלהים יבא
דבר שניהם הרי כאן אחד. ad ha'elohim yavo devar shneihem harei kan
echad. You only start by counting the second one. That's one. אשר
ירשיעון אלהים הרי כאן שנים. asher yarshi'un elohim harei kan shnayim. That's
two. ואין בית דין שקול, ve'ein beis din shakol, but once I
get to two, I can get to three. Okay? Because since you
can't have an even court, מוסיפין עלינו עוד אחד הרי כאן שלשה.
mosifin aleinu od echad harei kan shlosha. You add one and then
you get to three. Alright, so basically we all agree you get
to three. The only question is whether you got there because of
the principle that you don't have an even court, or did we
get to it because you were able to count the first occurrence?
So the גמרא Gemara says, so what's the debate? נימא בדרשין תחילה
קמיפלגי. neima bidorshin techilla kamifligi. It sounds like they're debating a general
hermeneutic principle. The general hermeneutic principle is, when you want to count
multiple occurrences of a word to get you to some conclusion, which
the גמרא Gemara does very often, can you count the first occurrence
of the word?
Okay. מר סבר דורשין תחילה, mar savar dorshin techilla, one says you
do, you are able to count the first occurrence, ומר סבר אין
דורשין תחילה, umar savar ein dorshin techilla, you're not. Yeah, that certainly
seems to be what they're debating. So the גמרא Gemara says, לא.
lo. No, not necessarily. דכולי עלמא אין דורשין תחילה. dekulei alma ein
dorshin techilla. Everybody could say you don't count the first occurrence.
So then how does, so then how do you, but that's not
true. רבי יאשיה Rabbi Yoshiya did count the first occurrence. So, לא,
lo, דכולי עלמא אין דורשין תחילה. dekulei alma ein dorshin techilla. אמר
לך רבי יאשיה, amar lach Rabbi Yoshiya, but רבי יאשיה Rabbi Yoshiya
says here's an exception. אם כן, im ken, if the תורה Torah
didn't want us to count the first occurrence, נימא קרא ונקרב בעל
הבית אל השופט מאי אל האלהים שמע מינה למנינא. neima kra venikrav
ba'al habayis el hashofet mai el ha'elohim shma mina leminyana. He basically
says, look, the fact that it uses the same word over and
over and over again, אלהים, Elohim, אלהים, Elohim, אלהים, Elohim, it could
have used another word. Okay? So the choice of the same word
and using it three times is to tell us each word should
be counted. Because if it didn't want us to count the first
word, it would have said שופט shofet and then it would have
said אלהים Elohim twice afterwards. Okay. רבי יונתן, Rabbi Yonatan, and רבי
יונתן Rabbi Yonatan says, no. לישנא דעלמא נקט. lishna de'alma nakat. The
reason it said אלהים Elohim the first time was just a normal
way of talking. What does that mean? כדאמרי אינשי, kide'amrei inshi, like
people say, מאן דאית ליה דינא ליקרב לגבי דיינא. man de'is lei
dina likrav legabei dayana. A person who has a court case should
go to a judge. So what does that mean? What's the point
of that little saying? What is that proving? So רש"י Rashi says,
רש"י Rashi has an explanation, but I think what he's saying is,
רש"י Rashi doesn't say this but what I think he's saying is
the following, is that the תורה, Torah, it's true, אלהים, Elohim, אלהים,
Elohim, אלהים, Elohim, it sounds redundant, and it sounds redundant you're supposed
to count the first time. But he says no. Sometimes people talk
in a like alliterative way or an echoing way as a way
of talking. The phrase is, if you've got a דין, din, you
go to a דיין. dayan. Okay? So why don't you say if
you have a דין din you go to a שופט? shofet? Because
it sounds nicer to say if you got a דין din you
go to a דיין, dayan, right? דין din and דיין. dayan. So
the תורה Torah wants to say אלהים, Elohim, אלהים, Elohim, אלהים, Elohim,
it's like sort of like self-referencing and echoing itself, but that's not
to indicate that every one of those instances should be counted. The
first one is still the פשט. pshat. Okay. So that seems to
be what the גמרא Gemara is saying. Maybe technically רבי יאשיה Rabbi
Yoshiya would agree in general you don't count the first occurrence, but
here he says you do because the תורה Torah went out of
its way to say use the same word three times. Okay? Whereas
the answer is, no, maybe that's just stylistic. Alright, but anyway, the
simpler read of course is, is that that is what they're debating.
This hermeneutic principle of do you normally count the first occurrence of
a word or not.
Yes. Isn't it possible that maybe שופט shofet doesn't denote an אלהים?
Elohim?
I know, that's what רש"י Rashi says. I was bracketing that. Okay.
So now the גמרא Gemara continues like this. ורבי יונתן, veRabbi Yonatan,
oh I just did that. Okay. רבי יאשיה לית ליה בית דין
נוטה? Rabbi Yoshiya leis lei beis din noteh? Now the גמרא Gemara
asks makes an interesting move. It says, you know, okay. So רבי
יאשיה Rabbi Yoshiya counted three occurrences. But why didn't רבי יאשיה Rabbi
Yoshiya do the same thing that רבי יונתן Rabbi Yonatan did? All
you really need is two, and once you have two you can
get to three. Why did he feel he needed three? I mean,
for us I think, for me, רבי יאשיה Rabbi Yoshiya is much
more elegant. Three אלהים, Elohims, three judges. But the גמרא Gemara sort
of said, well, why is it needed? Why didn't he just say
two, and then you get from two you can get to three?
Maybe, are we supposed to infer from this that according to רבי
יאשיה Rabbi Yoshiya you really could have an even בית דין? beis
din? Because if you couldn't have an even בית דין, beis din,
he really it would have been enough to have just had two,
and from there he could have gotten to three. Okay? So that's
what the גמרא Gemara says. רבי יאשיה לית ליה בית דין נוטה?
Rabbi Yoshiya leis lei beis din noteh? Does רבי יאשיה Rabbi Yoshiya
not need a בית דין beis din to be a tilting בית
דין, beis din, meaning he doesn't need a בית דין beis din
to have an odd number of people on it? Is that really
true?
והתניא, vehatanya, we taught in a
ברייתא, braisa, רבי אלעזר בנו של רבי יוסי הגלילי אומר, Rabbi Elazar
bno shel Rabbi Yosi haGlili omer, מה תלמוד לומר לנטות אחרי רבים
להטות, ma talmud lomar lintos acharei rabim lehatos, you should incline after
the majority, הטיה אמר עשה לך בית דין נוטה. hataya amar asei
lecha beis din noteh. Your בית דין beis din has to be
that word לנטות, lintos, your בית דין beis din has to be
able to be tipped. It has to be an odd number. So
shouldn't רבי יאשיה Rabbi Yoshiya hold of that? And if רבי יאשיה
Rabbi Yoshiya holds of that, shouldn't two be, he should just be
able to learn out two, and from two he should be able
to get to three. So
the גמרא Gemara says,
no. Surprisingly, סבר לה כרבי יהודה. savar lah keRabbi Yehuda. No, you
know what? Maybe you're right. Maybe רבי יאשיה Rabbi Yoshiya would say
that you can have an even בית דין, beis din, right? How
do you know that? Because רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda holds that in
our משנה, mishna, דאמר שבעים. de'amar shivim. Rabbi Yehuda says that the
סנהדרין *Sanhedrin* could be שבעים *shivim*, not שבעים ואחד *shivim v'echad*. So
you know what? There are opinions that you can have an even
בית דין *Beis Din*. Maybe that's what רבי יאשיה *Rabbi Yoshiya* holds.
דתנן *d'tnan* we taught in our משנה *Mishnah*: סנהדרין גדולה הייתה של
שבעים ואחד *Sanhedrin Gedolah haysa shel shivim v'echad*. רבי יהודה אומר שבעים
*Rabbi Yehuda omer shivim*. Rabbi Yehuda says seventy. So you're right. Maybe
רבי יאשיה *Rabbi Yoshiya* could in theory hold of an even בית
דין *Beis Din* and that's why he needed three אלוהים *Elohim*. The
גמרא *Gemara* says one minute. אימור דשמעת ליה לרבי יהודה בסנהדרי גדולה
*Eimur d'shamas leh l'Rabbi Yehuda b'Sanhedri Gedolah*. When does רבי יהודה *Rabbi
Yehuda* say you could have seventy? That's in the one instance of
the supreme בית דין *Beis Din*, the סנהדרין גדולה *Sanhedrin Gedolah*. דכתיב
קרא שבעים זקנים שבעים איש *d'chsiv kra shivim zekenim shivim ish*. So
that's a special פסוק *pasuk*. בשאר בית דינא מי שמעת ליה *B'sha'ar
beis dina mi shamas leh*? He never would say that you could
have an even בית דין *Beis Din* in any other one of
the בתי דין *Batei Din*. And I can even prove it to
you. וכי תימא לא שנא *v'chi teima lo shna*, you'll say well
maybe not, maybe if he says seventy there, maybe he holds other
בתי דין *Batei Din* could also be even numbered? No. דהתנן *d'hasnan*
our משנה *Mishnah* says: סמיכת זקנים *smichas zekenim*, the elders that put
their hands on in the case of the פר העלם דבר *par
helam davar*
ועגלה ערופה *v'egla arufa* בשלושה *bishlosha* is three, דברי רבי שמעון *divrei
Rabbi Shimon*. רבי יהודה אומר בחמישה *Rabbi Yehuda omer b'chamisha*, five. And
how does he get five? ואמינא מאי טעמא דרבי יהודה *v'amina mai
ta'ama d'Rabbi Yehuda*? What's his reasoning? וסמכו *v'samchu* it says when it
talks about their putting their hands on the calf, it says וסמכו
*v'samchu* is שנים *shnayim*. I'm sorry, this is the head of the
פר העלם דבר *par helam davar*, excuse me, about the first case,
about the ox that's brought for when they בית דין *Beis Din*
rules incorrectly. So וסמכו *v'samchu* they is two, זקני *ziknei* the elders
שנים *shnayim* is two. So that gets you four. ואין בית דין
שקול *v'ein beis din shakol*, now you can't have a בית דין
*Beis Din* of an even number. מוסיפין עליהן עוד אחד הרי כאן
חמישה *mosifin aleihen od echad harei kan chamisha*, five. So the point
being that רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* who says that the סנהדרין *Sanhedrin*
was שבעים *shivim*, only acknowledges an odd number of judges on other
בתי דין *Batei Din*. And actually the דרשה *drasha* that we have
for him is that he would have gotten to an idea of
four, but he can't have an even number and that led him
to an idea of five. So clearly other than the סנהדרין *Sanhedrin*,
nobody holds of an idea of an even בית דין *Beis Din*.
So wouldn't רבי יאשיה *Rabbi Yoshiya* say the same thing? So the
גמרא *Gemara* says: רבי יאשיה עדיפא מדרבי יהודה *Rabbi Yoshiya adifa mi'd'Rabbi
Yehuda*. No, maybe רבי יאשיה *Rabbi Yoshiya* is taking רבי יהודה *Rabbi
Yehuda* one step further. דאילו רבי יהודה בסנהדרי גדולה הוא דלית ליה
*d'ilu Rabbi Yehuda b'Sanhedri Gedolah hu d'leis leh*. Rabbi Yehuda would say
the large סנהדרין *Sanhedrin* of seventy, that can be does not need
to be an odd number. הא בשאר בית דינא אית ליה *ha
b'sha'ar beis dina is leh*, other בתי דין *Batei Din* need to
be an odd number, like we just demonstrated for רבי יהודה *Rabbi
Yehuda*. ואילו רבי יאשיה בשאר בית דינא נמי לית ליה *v'ilu Rabbi
Yoshiya b'sha'ar beis dina nami leis leh*. He can always live with
an even number בית דין *Beis Din*. Very strange. Since רבי יאשיה
*Rabbi Yoshiya* had to learn from the three occurrences of אלוהים *Elohim*,
we're going to infer from that that two wouldn't have been enough
for him because with two he could have been happy with a
בית דין *Beis Din* of an even number. And therefore in his
he basically accepts the idea that you can have a בית דין
*Beis Din* of an even number. And that's why the תורה *Torah*
had to be clear that this בית דין *Beis Din* needed three
because you could not have gone from two to three. So now
let's just wrap this up, two more lines. So the גמרא *Gemara*
says: ואלא האי לנטות מאי עביד ליה *v'ela hai l'intos mai avid
leh*? One minute, if רבי יאשיה *Rabbi Yoshiya* can have a בית
דין *Beis Din* of an even number, what did he do with
the פסוק *pasuk* that says you incline after the majority, which presumably
means even one person? So מוקים לה בדיני נפשות *mookim lah b'dinei
nefashos*. Oh, that's for a capital case. That requires an odd number.
The גמרא *Gemara* says what? אבל בדיני ממונות לא *aval b'dinei mamonos
lo*? What, you're telling me that in a monetary case you don't
go by a majority rule? ואלא הא דתנן שניים אומרים זכאי ואחד
אומר חייב זכאי *v'ela ha d'tnan shnayim omrim zakai v'echad omer chayav
zakai*. If two say innocent and one says guilty, he's innocent. שניים
אומרים חייב ואחד אומר זכאי חייב *shnayim omrim chayav v'echad omer zakai
chayav*. Two say guilty, one says innocent, he's guilty. So נימא דלא
כרבי יאשיה *neima d'lo k'Rabbi Yoshiya*? You're going to say רבי יאשיה
*Rabbi Yoshiya* doesn't hold of the principle that you go by a
single person to weight towards a majority? So אפילו תימא רבי יאשיה
*afilu teima Rabbi Yoshiya*. Fine, fine, fine. Of course רבי יאשיה *Rabbi
Yoshiya* holds that the decision of a court is decided by a
majority. מייתי לה בקל וחומר מדיני נפשות *maisi leh b'kal vachomer mi'dinei
nefashos*. Once דיני נפשות dinei nefashot *dinei nefashos* goes by majority, דיני
ממונות dinei mamonot. *dinei mamonos* goes by majority. Bottom line is the
פסוק *pasuk* of לנטות *l'hatos* what?
How do you learn קל וחומר *kal vachomer* from נפשות *nefashos* to
ממונות *mamonos*?
If if by if
someone's life can be decided by a majority rule, certainly a monetary
issue can be decided by a majority rule. Okay, but the clear
point is, the real punchline is going to be the end, which
is, let's just get to the last sentence, it makes it all
clear. ומה דיני נפשות דחמירי אמר רחמנא זיל בתר רובא דיני ממונות
לא כל שכן *u'mah dinei nefashos d'chamiri amar Rachmana zil basar ruba
dinei mamonos lo kol sheken*. If דיני נפשות *dinei nefashos* if someone's
life can be decided by majority, certainly someone's money. So meaning the
point being though that the פסוק *pasuk* of לנטות אחרי רבים *l'hatos
acharei rabim* is telling you procedurally how does a court decide? What
does it mean for a court to rule? It means the majority
of judges. The majority of judges decides a capital case. capital crime,
it decides a civil case, but what it doesn't tell you is
that the court has to be made up of an odd number.
So you can have a court of an even number, then you
could have a split court and no decision. That's obviously the problem.
Okay, but the point the גמרא is doing is distinguishing between the
number on the court and the procedure of deciding. And it's speculating
or
hypothesizing with very I think thin evidence, but that רבי אושעיא Rabbi
Oshaya might be okay with a court made up of an even
number of judges, but of course he would agree to the principle
that a court comes to a decision based on the majority members
of the court. And that's true both in דיני נפשות and then
of course in דיני ממונות. Okay, so we'll end here for today.